A Finding Aid to the Paul Bransom Papers, 1862-1985 bulk 1904-1979, in the Archives of American Art AAA.branpaul
Archives of American Art
- Scrapbooks, circa 1880s-1970s; Series 7; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 8 and 11
  - Items Found Tucked Between Pages of Volume II, undated; (See also Box 11) (Box 8, Folder 27)
    (photographs of Paul and Grace Bransom, photographs of works of art by Paul Bransom, photograph of oil on canvas portrait of Bransom by Dan Green)
  - Photographs Removed from Volume II, circa 1886-1970 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    (Childhood photographs of Paul Bransom; family members; nanny; Paul and Grace Bransom in Canada Lake, NY home and studio; Paul Bransom painting)
  - Oversized Scrapbook (See Box 8, f26) (Box 11 (sol))
  - Oversized Items Found Tucked Between Pages of Volume II (See Box 8, f27) (Box 11 (sol))
- Artwork, 1903-1976; Series 8; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 8-9, OV 13-22
  This series includes sketchbooks, sketches, drawings, designs, illustrations, cartoons, and prints by Paul Bransom, and artwork of various media by other artists. Most of the artwork depicts wildlife and other animals, although drawings of landscapes, flora, and people are also found.
  Sketches, drawings, and designs encompass the bulk of this series. Three sketching expeditions from the 1920s are represented. The drawings from the Green Tree racehorse stables in Saratoga Springs are accompanied by an essay recounting the trip. Additional material related to the New Mexico Lion Hunt is found in Notes and Writings. The remainder of miscellaneous sketches, drawings, and designs in this series depict a wide range of subjects in various media, from preliminary rough sketches to very finished drawings. Subjects include domestic animals, North American and African wildlife, flora, landscapes, and narrative subjects for illustrations, usually also with animal subjects. Included are works in charcoal, pencil, pastel, watercolor, and ink.
  Prints by Bransom include a series of 26 monotype prints, lithographs, and several woodblock prints, some of which are for bookplates and Christmas cards.
  Many of the works of art in this series are signed and/or annotated by Paul Bransom. A few have an inventory number written on them beginning with "E/B," which refers to the artwork inventory created by Mario Cesar Romero. Additional documentation of this inventory project is found in Personal Business Records. Bibliographic information about Bransom's illustrations is also found in Personal Business records. Notes listing artwork and exhibitions can be found in Notes and Writings. Additional artwork, including illustrated letters and cards, is found in Correspondence. See series descriptions for further details.
  - Sketchbook, circa 1930-1940 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Sketchbook, Cattle Sketches, undated (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (Box 8)
    - Alabama Quail Hunt, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - New Mexico Lion Hunt, 1927; (See also OV 13) (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Green Tree Stables, Saratoga Springs, NY, 1929, undated; (See also OV 13) (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Miscellaneous Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, undated; (14 of 19 folders) (Box 8, Folder 34-47)
    - Miscellaneous Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, undated; (5 of 19 folders; see also OV 13-21) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 1-5)
  - "News From Bugville" Original Drawing, circa 1905; (See OV 22) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Design for Starr Family Shield, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 7)
  - Prints (Box 9 (hol))
    - Miscellaneous Prints, undated; (2 folders; see also OV 22) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 8-9)
    - Linoleum Blocks, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 10)
    - Proofs, 1947, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 11)
    - Test Prints, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Artwork By Others (Box 9 (hol))
    - Cartoon by Clare Victor "Dwig" Dwiggins, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 13)
    - Painting by O.F. von Feuher, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 14)
    - Painting by Al Gilbert, 1976 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 15)
    - Sketch of Bransom by Everett Hibbard, 1973 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 16)
    - Bookplate by Lionel Lindsay, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 17)
    - Print by Benson Moore, 1974 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 18)
    - Drawing Signed "MCO", undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 19)
    - Paintings and Drawings by Charles Sarka, 1903-1910, 1946, 1956, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 20)
    - Print by R. Harmer Smith, 1973 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 21)
    - Painting by Marion Terry, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 22)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 8, f32-33; and Box 9, f5) (Box 13 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5) (Box 14 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5) (Box 15 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5) (Box 16 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5) (Box 17 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5) (Box 18 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5) (Box 19 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5) (Box 20 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (Copies) (Box 21 (OV))
  - Oversized "News From Bugville" Original Drawing (See B9, f6) (Box 22 (OV))
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Prints (See B9, f9) (Box 22 (OV))
  - Oversized Artwork by Al Gilbert (See B9, f15) (Box 22 (OV))